<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The eye of faith open to God unfolded in a sermon preached at the funerall of that vertuous and religious gentlewoman,  Mrs. Julian Blackvvell, together with a narration of her vertuous life and  happy death / by John Sedgvvick ...</title>
            <author>Sedgwick, John, 1600 or 1601-1643.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1640</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 100 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 71 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11846</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22149.7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S3177</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">33143113</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 33143113</idno>
            <idno type="VID">28236</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11846)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 28236)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1883:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The eye of faith open to God unfolded in a sermon preached at the funerall of that vertuous and religious gentlewoman,  Mrs. Julian Blackvvell, together with a narration of her vertuous life and  happy death / by John Sedgvvick ...</title>
                  <author>Sedgwick, John, 1600 or 1601-1643.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[18], 112 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by George Miller,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXL [1640]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Imprinamtur Tho. Wykes. Iuly 30. 1640."</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁶, a⁴, B-E¹², F⁸.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Blackwell, Julian, d. 1640.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms CXLI, 8 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:28236:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:28236:1"/>
            <p>THE EYE OF FAITH <hi>open to GOD.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Vnfolded in a Sermon Preached at the Funerall of that vertuous and Religious Gentlewoman M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>. JVLIAN BLACKVVELL, <hi>together with a Narration of her ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Life and happy Death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By JOHN SEDGVVICK Batchelor of Divinity, and Preacher of GODS Word in <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <bibl>Prov 31. 30.</bibl>
            <q>Favour is deceitfull, and beauty is vaine: but a woman that feareth the Lord, ſhe ſhall be praiſed.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by GEORGE MILLER. MDCXL.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:28236:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:28236:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE <hi>WORSHIPFVLL</hi> IOHN BLACKVVELL Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, his Majeſties <hi>Grocer,</hi> comfort, and happy imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the deceaſed.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hilſt Miniſters preach Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Sermons, they find the wind ſetting in their faces from their auditors: ſome thinke that too little, others that too much, and
<pb facs="tcp:28236:3"/> moſt that what is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken concerning the dead is but formality or flattery; They report that the <hi>Aethio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pians</hi> doe picture Angels black, and Divels white, and I thinke that they<note place="margin">Amandus Polanus Syntag. Theol lib. 20 c. 17.</note> juſtly ſuffer cenſure who doe knowingly <hi>call evill good and good evill:</hi> yet I deeme, that meete and juſt praiſe is a due to Gods Saints departed, and<note place="margin">Salatia vivorum, non ſuffra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuorum. Orationes Aug.</note> though they add not to their honour and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe being in Heaven; yet they may proove both comforts and inſtructions to the living left upon
<pb facs="tcp:28236:3"/> earth; eſpecially to ſuch who forgoe thoſe with griefe whom they for a time enjoyed with love; I doe not ſend the living to the dead with Papiſts, yet let mee tell you, that there are theſe things comfortable to the living from the dead. 1. Their holineſſe of life, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in death, grounded evidences for our hope of their future happineſſe: And 2. That there ſhall be a time of meeting and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying each other againe at the laſt day, ſuch being not loſt but gone before
<pb facs="tcp:28236:4"/> us; add to this the good of their examples (which are of great force) for the teaching of poſterity; who may take them for their patterne, and ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble them in their religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous courſes, that they may ſeeme to ſurvive in them: both theſe ends are my aime in publiſhing this Sermon, and with it the juſt teſtimony which I gave unto your late loving and beloved Wife, whom death hath freed from all ſinfull and ſorrowfull evils, and brought to the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of her God in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens
<pb facs="tcp:28236:4"/> happineſſe; ſhee well knew that the world could never make her fully hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py; and that Chriſtians are never in their beſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, till that they are in their heavenly condition; I deſire not to renew your griefe, but to ſhew that I had a ſhare in your loſſe of that Iewell laid up by God in the higheſt Heavens; whom all your care and coſt (which did demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate you to be a loving Husband) could not lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger continue on earth: whilſt ſhee was yours, you did (I confeſſe) what could
<pb facs="tcp:28236:5"/> be done for her credit, comfort, and continuance, and thereby deſerved from her that praiſe which of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſhee gave of you to my ſelfe and others; but being gone, there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines a double monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of her; one of her owne, for ſhee hath left with you thoſe in whom ſhee liveth, whom (I need not ſay to you) you muſt love as a Father, and a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle the more for the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſake; another of mine in this Publication, wherein her memory is made pretious among the
<pb facs="tcp:28236:5"/> Saints, and perpetuated unto all poſterity; a Worke done by mee up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your owne earneſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaty, and therefore can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but be welcome un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you. You have your deſire, let mee have mine. Thinke of your loſſe; and remember your ſelfe, and place, in which God hath ſet you; doing things ſo, that your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort within, and credit without, may ſtill be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held in the Churches of God, amongſt whom you have obtain'd an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent name: I need
<pb facs="tcp:28236:6"/> to ſay no more to you, but that I am</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your much obliged friend, Io: Sedgvvick.</signed>
               <dateline>From my houſe in S. <hi>Dunſtances</hi> in the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> London.</dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:28236:6"/>
            <head>To the Reader, and in ſpeciall to my worthy good Friends, in and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>about the City of <hi>London,</hi> Peace, and ſetling of mind.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſhaking of<note place="margin">A double temper of men in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mes of danger.</note> the water doth not more diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the mudd that's at the bottome, nor the beating of the pulſe the diſtemper of the body; then Times of Danger doe
<pb facs="tcp:28236:7"/> bewray men in point of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, or exceſse: now men ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare<note place="margin">1. To be careleſſe.</note> either to be careleſſe and graceleſly ſecure, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving their eyes bound up, and their conſciences ſo ſeared, that they neither ſee or feare any danger: or to be over-fearing: having their<note place="margin">2. To be over feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</note> eyes too open upon, or their hearts too much affected with the ſadneſſe, and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the times; the first ſort I leave to the vanity of their minde, and ſinfull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their courſes, aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them that their conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance in carnall ſecurity is to them an evident fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runner
<pb facs="tcp:28236:7"/> of their future miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: the latter ſort I ſhall adviſe to conſider of theſe two things: Firſt, that the<note place="margin">The Springs of over-much fearing.</note> over-much fearing of mans heart in evill times doth ariſe, from a falſe eye, or a wrong foundation: I meane the eye, and the Arme of fleſh; he that at ſuch time hath no other eye to ſee withall, then that by which he ſeeth every thing, or being able to pierce no deeper, or looke no higher then naturall reaſon, or out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward objects can helpe him, ſhall be ſure to finde that his ſenſes will faile him, and his troubles ſinke him:
<pb facs="tcp:28236:8"/> Beſides, the <hi>Arme of Fleſh</hi> truſted unto, and relied upon, will make him to ebb and flow, and ſhall hold his ſpirit in a courſe of ſuch constant agitation, that in the end he ſhall flagg and faint: Fleſh at the beſt is too weake a prop to ſtay the ſoule, a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine impeacher, and empai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer of mans confidence, and comfort; and who ſo doe put it into the place of a god, ſhall undoubtedly find from it the deceivings of a creature. Secondly, that the beſt way to quit our ſelves of an over-fearing heart in the daies of trouble, is to get
<pb facs="tcp:28236:8"/> an eye of Faith, which alone ſhuts up the eye of ſenſe, and getteth ſuch views of Gods Love, Power, and provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that God is knowne to be, and alſo made the ſole ſtay, and ſtaffe of the ſoule; upon whom whoſoever truly trusteth he is in ſuch ſafety, that no malice of men or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels can endanger him. My Brethren, had we the Angeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call eyes of faith, we ſhould feare leſſe; though times vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſenſe are distreſſefull, and almoſt deſperate: this alone can ſee a better iſſue then carnall reaſon can apprehend, and an higher power to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect
<pb facs="tcp:28236:9"/> and guard then humane helpes are either liekly or able to affoord; this will make a man waite till the fifth Scene of the Tragedy is acted, knowing that troubles have their turnings, as ſpring-tides have their eb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bings: This eye <hi>David</hi> had in his troubles, as the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Diſcourſe will ſhew you, and this eye I wiſh unto you all, that your confidences and comforts may abound: and though I hope that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of you have this eye, yet beholding your dimneſſe, and weakneſſe, I have ſent unto you theſe following Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb facs="tcp:28236:9"/> upon a Text given unto mee, to preach on at the Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall of Miſtriſſe <hi>Iulian Black well,</hi> and I deſire that they may have the ſame worke upon you that was wrought upon <hi>Eliſha's</hi> ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, that by them you may be enabled to rid your mindes of thoſe baſe and unbeleeving feares, wherewithall you have beene too long and too much aſſaulted and perplex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and may direct your ſoules amid your troubleſome cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, and diſtractions to your onely reſting place, namely, the ſtrong God in whom all ſafety and ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb facs="tcp:28236:10"/> is to be found, which is the onely thing aimed at in the publique Preaching, and ſought for in the private prayers of him that is your daily remembrancer,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>IO: SEDGVVICK.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:28236:10"/>
            <head>THE Eye of faith open to GOD.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>PSAL. 141. VER. 8.</bibl>
               <q>But mine eyes are unto thee O God the Lord, in thee is my truſt, leave not my ſoule deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OD was with <hi>David</hi> in love, and <hi>David</hi> was with God in life and that in every condition of his life;
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:28236:11"/> the Context doth render <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> in a very ſad calamitous condition, and the Text doth report him unto us in an holy and Chriſtian carriage to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his God, for his eyes were upon him, his confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in him, and his prayer unto him: a fit behaviour for all Chriſtians in ſorrow and diſtreſſe:</p>
            <p>The words containe two parts,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. A beleeving profeſſion laid downe in two choiſe actions reſpecting God as their chiefe object, and they are
<list>
                     <item>1. The carriage of his eyes from men to God, <hi>Mine eyes are unto thee O God the Lord.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. The planting or
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:28236:11"/> firme placing of his truſt or confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in God the Lord, <hi>in thee is my truſt.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>2. An hearty petition, the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted evidence of his beleeving profeſſion (<hi>a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving heart is a praying heart) Leave not my ſoule deſtitute.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>From the whole we ſee,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Note.</hi> The god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly doe know the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves both in their graces an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> practiſes.</note> that good men do know their owne tempers in grace, and ſpeake their owne practiſes in godlineſſe; <hi>David</hi> did not vaunt himſelfe out of pride, but humbly expreſſeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in that carriage which doth belong unto all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in their ſad and diſtreſſed conditions; I ſee no reaſon why Chriſtians may not ſpeake of their gratious practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:28236:12"/> ſo be they doe it ſincerely, humbly, for inſtruction of others; may not all ages learne from <hi>David</hi> how to compoſe their affections and diſpoſe their ſoules in evill times? but come wee more cloſely to the words.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mine eyes are unto thee O God the Lord:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whence I conclude,</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Doct.</note>
               <hi>That in calamitous and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſefull conditions, Chriſtians have or ſhould have their eyes unto God the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When <hi>Iehoſaphat</hi> and the people were in great diſtreſſe, and the times were full of feares and dangers, inſomuch that all humane power and policie failed them, (for the Text ſaith, <hi>They knew not what to, doe</hi>) then they had their eyes unto God; they ſay, <hi>But our</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chron. 10. 12.</note>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:28236:12"/> 
               <hi>eyes are upon thee.</hi> When <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 7. 5 56.</note> was ſtoning hee looked up ſtedfaſtly into Heaven and ſaw the glory of God, when <hi>David</hi> was in danger and the Church in Captivity, they did lift up their eyes to the<note place="margin">Pſa. 121. 1</note> hills from whence came their helpe, and had their eyes to God that dwelleth in the Heavens. For the opening of<note place="margin">123. 1.</note> the point obſerve theſe things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that Gods eyes of mercy and compaſſion are as ſurely upon his to behold them for their good, as their eyes can be believingly upon him in the expectation of good from him, a Chriſtian looketh up to God, and God looketh downe on a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, the Chriſtian ſaith, <hi>O Lord mine eyes are unto thee,</hi> and God
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:28236:13"/> ſaith, <hi>O Chriſtian mine are upon thee,</hi> ſure I am; that eye an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth to eye, no man can looke up, but God will looke downe upon him, hence ſaith God, <hi>Surely I have ſeene the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 3. 7.</note> 
               <hi>of my people which are in Egypt,</hi> they looked up to God in their groanings and cries, and God lookes downe upon them, in a mercifull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding and relieving of them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that there are two ſorts of eyes by which men doe looke up unto God.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. One are the eyes of the<note place="margin">Eyes of tvvo ſorts.</note> body, which wee may call the eyes of ſence.</item>
               <item>2. The other are the eyes of the ſoule, which are called the eyes of Faith.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The point is true of both,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:28236:13"/> though the latter be inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, that a Chriſtian may have God before his eyes, as well as his eyes unto God in times of affl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ctions, the<note place="margin">God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the eyes, vvhat?</note> former doth note an act of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verentiall and awfull reſpect begot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en in the ſoule towards Gods Majeſty at ſuch times eſpecially: for when ſhould men more awe God, and reverence before him, then when they are in and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der trouble? the latter doth note the advancings of the ſoule by the workings of<note place="margin">The eyes unto God, vvhat?</note> Faith, to a looking for the promiſed good from God to a man in and under afflictions; and this is the thing I am to ſpeake of, which I thus open to you.</p>
            <p>1. That there are many
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:28236:14"/> ſpeciall promiſes for good un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſtians in all (eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) their afflicted conditions, yea God hath promiſed to make every condition good, according to that of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>All things ſhall worke</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 18.</note> 
               <hi>together for good,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Simile.</note>even the croſſe going of the wheeles ſhall further the right going of the clock.</p>
            <p>2. That the heart of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian is much lifted up after the enjoyment of the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed good; wee doe naturally feare evill, and deſire good, and though we doe ſee that a man may doe us hurt, yet our eyes are not upon him that he ſhould doe us hurt, the Scripture phraſe is, <hi>I looked for</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 30. 26</note> 
               <hi>good, and I waited for light.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. That the ſoule never advanceth it ſelfe to looke up
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:28236:14"/> in a waiting and expecting way untill it is made belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving: unbeleeving men have no God to looke unto, nay they are blinde and without eyes towards God, it is Faith that is the hand that opens the doore, and helpes the eye to looke in and upon God, this gives light, and ſight unto the ſoule, having the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the body, and ſoule, and ſences in exerciſing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves upon God, I ſay Faith hath her ſences, it is a grace in the ſoule that hath feete whereby ſhee goes to God, hands whereby ſhee doth take hold of God, armes wherewith ſhe doth embrace God, eares whereby ſhee doth heare God, and eyes whereby ſhee doth looke up to God; in a word, it is a
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:28236:15"/> ſoule within the ſoule, and a body within the body, not an eye, but eyes, which is enough for the viſion and fruition of God, and it's whole worke is to bring in the ſoule unto God, and to determine it ſelfe in God, it takes much pleaſure in God, and ſatisfies it ſelfe with God at all times; <q>the ſoule by it is caſt into this frame of reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning dependance, God hath ſaid that hee will doe mee good in all my conditions, and I have his word for it which is ſure, and unchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, when I ſhall be anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red I know not, but that I ſhall be anſwered I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident; this one thing will I doe, I will ſtill keep to my God, and never give off the word of his promiſe, for I
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:28236:15"/> know that hee will doe mee good in his time; I will ſet mee downe and reſt mee quiet in his word, waiting upon him, and looking for him, beleeving that he will never fruſtrate my expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, this is, or ſhould be the carriage of the eyes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God.</q>
            </p>
            <p>4. That we do not narrow up this carriage of a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans ſoule towards God onely to the times of miſery and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe, wee muſt know that the eyes of Chriſtians are up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God in all conditions of their lives, in times of proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity they eye him, and obſerve him as well as in times of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity; but herein is the truth and power of their <hi>Faith</hi> ſeene, that no darke or dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous condition can hinder
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:28236:16"/> them from looking up unto God, ſuppoſe that fleſh and blood doth interpoſe by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary reaſonings, and that the outward condition ſeemes to goe contrary unto a promiſe, ſo that it ſhall be all night and no day, all ſorrow and no joy, yet a Chriſtian that is in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and hath no light, hath by the power and preſence of <hi>Faith,</hi> a <hi>God</hi> to goe to, and to looke upon: nothing can take off his dependance upon God, and expectation of good from God: reade <hi>Iſa.</hi> 50. 10. and <hi>Hab.</hi> 3. 17, 18.</p>
            <p>4. Fiftly, that all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans doe not equally caſt their eyes upon <hi>God</hi> in evill times; it is true, they have all eyes, and all a <hi>God</hi> to looke unto, and upon, yet for as much as they have not all an equall
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:28236:16"/> meaſure of light in revelation, nor an equall meaſure of aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance for application, their expectations of good from <hi>God</hi> cannot be equall: expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience doth teach us, that ſome mens eyes are upon <hi>God</hi> with victory and conqueſt over the Arguments of ſence and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and the workings of feares and doubts; other Chriſtians have their eyes as truely upon <hi>God,</hi> but it is with much weakneſſe and many combates; I alas! they have much a doe to looke up, and it may be they are ſo farre from an evidentiall looking upon <hi>God,</hi> that their expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is onely habituall and their whole life is the longing and endevour of their ſoules to bring their eyes unto God.</p>
            <p>6. Sixtly, that even a <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:28236:17"/> whoſe faith carries his eyes upwards towards <hi>God</hi> in his promiſes and name of mercy, may have his eyes at ſometime downeward even below his deſire; I cannot conceive that hee ſo ſixt his eyes on <hi>God,</hi> but that as he was man and did walke on the earth, he had his eyes on the earth to direct his going; and as hee was a Chriſtian, the eyes of his ſoule were ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times downewards, for <hi>Faith</hi> would make him to be loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king into himſelfe, ſo as hee did ſee into his owne ſinfull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and unworthineſſe; and againe, if we take him as hee was in trouble and miſery, I doubt not to affirme that his eyes were too open upon the ſame, and that he did looke downe upon the roaring and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:28236:17"/> raging of the Sea to the q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of his Spirit, and the failing in thoſe degrees of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation which formerly he found in himſelfe, I ſay hee was not onely ſenſible, but over ſenſible of his troubles, and was ſo up and downe in his expectations, that even periſhing thoughts take hold of him, for he ſaith, <hi>One day</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 27 1.</note> 
               <hi>I ſhall die by the hands of Saul,</hi> Neither <hi>David</hi> nor any Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian can hold up his Faith in looking unto <hi>God</hi> at all times alike: but thus it is with them, at ſometimes they are higher, at ſometimes lower, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſtronger, and ſometimes weaker in their dependance.</p>
            <p>But whence is it that they have their eyes upon <hi>God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I conceive it ſprings from theſe cauſes: Firſt, becauſe
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:28236:18"/> 
               <hi>God</hi> and they ſtand in relative termes each unto other: wee ſay there is no comfort in an abſolute <hi>God</hi> ſtanding by himſelfe diſtant from the ſoule; but in a relative <hi>God</hi> made over in covenant unto his: ſo that it is the mutuall relations that are made and eſtabliſhed in the Covenant betwixt <hi>God</hi> and them, that makes them to fixe their eyes upon <hi>God:</hi> God is Father, and Friend, and Lord, and Husband, and Guide unto his children, and no marvaile if their eyes are upon him.</p>
            <p>Secondly, becauſe in <hi>God</hi> is an All-ſufficiencie for helpe and comfort in evill times, the creatures have an emptineſſe in them, and cannot become either foundation or comfort to a Chriſtian in and under his
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:28236:18"/> miſeries; but <hi>God</hi> is full and fit even one that exceeds all maladies, able to ſupply all wants, and to ſatisfie all cra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vings, he being an univerſall good, full Fountaine, and high hill, or mountaine ſet up for the Chriſtian to looke unto.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, becauſe of the promiſe of good which is made unto them by <hi>God;</hi> this is truth, that <hi>Faith</hi> is founded on the Promiſe, and the good that it doth expect is a promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed good; Now becauſe the ſoule hath the grant of a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, hereupon hath it a ground for expectation; for take away the promiſe, and the light is removed, and the eyes are ſo put out, that there is no turning of the ſoule to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>God;</hi> as the doore turnes upon the hinges, ſo
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:28236:19"/> doth the ſoule turne in a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving way upon the Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</p>
            <p>To apply this point.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> In the firſt place, it diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers unto us the want of <hi>Faith</hi> that is in wicked men in times of calamity; this we ſay of them, that their eyes are up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and unto the creatures both to ſee what they have done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt or can doe for them; they looke downe ward to the creatures, and have an eye of expectation of helpe from them, if they are ſick, they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in the hand of the Phyſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; if they are in danger, they runne to this houſe and that Tower; to this policie and that power, looking to be ſafe and ſecure in and by theſe meanes, if they are dying they flie to this creature and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:28236:19"/> that Saint; ſo that ſtill their eyes are creature-ward and earth-ward; wicked men in no condition can looke up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to <hi>God;</hi> in proſperity they ſcorne <hi>God</hi> and his will, and cannot looke unto him with an obſerving eye; and in times of adverſity they fall off from him, and doe not looke upon him with an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting eye, and in this they doe purchaſe to themſelves an increaſe of miſery here, and aſſurance of damnation here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after; no looking unto <hi>God,</hi> no comfort of conſcience in any condition.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Secondly, it may teach us to ſee if that our eyes are upon <hi>God</hi> in evill times; men doe juſtly cry out of the miſeries of ourtimes, and I thinke we may ſay, <hi>Wee have heard a</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 30. 5</note>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:28236:20"/> 
               <hi>voice of trembling there is feare, and not peace, alas! for</hi>
               <note place="margin">7.</note> 
               <hi>that day is great, ſo that none is like it, it is even the time of.</hi> Jacobs <hi>trouble.</hi> Our times are trembling times, and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blous times, and there is no Chriſtian man or woman but muſt needs confeſſe ſo much, and beſide the generall cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, we have the time of our particular miſery, our conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons either are, or have beene ſad and perplexed, tell mee now, where are your eyes fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? upon <hi>God?</hi> then it's well, and give mee leave to preſſe you to this triall upon this one ground, becauſe that multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of men have no eyes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>God</hi> in evill times.</p>
            <p>Surely if our eyes are upon <hi>God,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, we ſhall make <hi>God</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:28236:20"/> with us, beholding and regarding us in our miſeries; the eye doth make the object preſent to it ſelfe, and faith looking upon <hi>God,</hi> doth make <hi>God</hi> preſent to a Chriſtian; the truth is, that it's no miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry that can divide a Chriſtian and his <hi>God,</hi> for <hi>God</hi> hath tied his preſence and love with his children in the fire, and water, and priſon, and dungeon; and<note place="margin">Eſa. 43. 2.</note> it is as true that if the eye of faith be once rightly ſet upon <hi>God</hi> in times of trouble, there is no want of <hi>God</hi> to ſuch a ſoule; ſuch a one whoſe eyes are upon <hi>God,</hi> may want the company of neere and deere friends, they may be ſeque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tred and kept from him; but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he company of a <hi>God</hi> he can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ever want, a Chriſtian is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er without his <hi>God,</hi> ſo long
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:28236:21"/> as hee can keepe up the eye of his <hi>Faith</hi> upon God: <hi>Though I walke in the valley of the ſhadow of death, thou art with mee, thy rod and thy ſtaffe they comfort mee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O ſweet comfort and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py condition in times of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe! when the ſoule can ſay men are againſt mee, yet <hi>God</hi> is for mee; men are ſhut out from mee by men, but my <hi>God</hi> they cannot ſhut out from mee, the eye of <hi>Faith</hi> will bring downe <hi>God</hi> into a dungeon, and ſee him in a dungeon, and maketh a man to ſee no want of creature-company, becauſe he hath divine com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany.</p>
            <p>Secondly, wee ſhall have ſome comfortable repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>God</hi> unto us; it i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:28236:21"/> true in nature, that the eye in it ſelfe hath no colour, but all its colour is in the object; and I conceive that the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous diſcoveries of <hi>God</hi> are made over unto <hi>Faith;</hi> till the eye of <hi>Faith</hi> be erected in the ſoule, <hi>God</hi> is in darkneſſe to a man, let things have a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour<note place="margin">Simile.</note> and luſter in them, untill light come to make them cleare, they are as if they were not, ſo though there be a glory in <hi>God,</hi> yet to ſence and reaſon, <hi>God</hi> is a <hi>God</hi> in night and darkneſſe, or ſuch a one as cannot be eſpied and obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, but when <hi>Faith</hi> comes into the ſoule, now <hi>God</hi> is a <hi>God</hi> in the light, and the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian is enabled in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to enjoy the bleſſed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexe of <hi>God</hi> to his ſoule, whereby even in his greateſt
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:28236:22"/> miſery he is able to look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his <hi>God</hi> with that bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that the very beholding of his <hi>God</hi> in the way of <hi>Faith</hi> doth greatly joy and glad his ſoule, making him unſpeake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably glorious unto his ſoule, a man that lookes up to <hi>God</hi> ſhall ſee more grounds of comfort ſeated in <hi>God,</hi> then grounds of ſadneſſe in his troubles, the face of times cannot gather more blackneſſe or threaten more miſery; then <hi>Gods</hi> face doth promiſe and aſſure peace and protection; <hi>Faith</hi> ſeeth all the worſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, and beſt above in <hi>God</hi> and with <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, we ſhall be ravi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and greatly affected with the glories and beauties of <hi>God,</hi> viſion drawes on affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, or things doe affect the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:28236:22"/> ſoule by ſence, by looking we come to liking; the true cauſe why a wicked man doth neither joy in <hi>God</hi> or admire the beauties that are in <hi>God,</hi> is becauſe he wants eyes to look upon <hi>God,</hi> but the man whoſe eyes are opened, &amp; open unto <hi>God,</hi> takes notice of ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of grace and mercy in <hi>God,</hi> that his ſoule is taken with <hi>God,</hi> and rapt up into a holy raviſhment and admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; <q>Now he cries out who is a <hi>God</hi> like unto our <hi>God?</hi> O the Majeſty and mercy that is in him; I ſee that in him for mee and my neceſſity, that I cannot ſee in all the creatures put them together;</q> the ſoule doth now begin to feede it ſelfe and cheere it ſelfe in and upon <hi>God</hi> in the midſt of all afflictions making
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:28236:23"/> this to be its greateſt comfort, that it hath ſuch a <hi>God,</hi> who is ſo great a good to enjoy: <hi>Faith</hi> cannot looke up to its <hi>God</hi> without encreaſing of its confidence and comforts.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, we ſhall be ſet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a longing after <hi>God,</hi> and his comforts; the ſeeing of things ſtirres up deſires in us after them, ſo the looking up to <hi>God</hi> doth fill the ſoule with a fervent longing after the <hi>Lord;</hi> the Chriſtian that lookes up hopes: the ſoule in this caſe is much after the manner of a tender wife, who looking for her Husband by ſuch a day, or ſuch an hower, ſhee is faint and full of griefe untill that day come, and when the day is come, ſhee runnes to the doore and window to ſee if he be not comming, being much
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:28236:23"/> troubled that hee is not yet come, ſurely all the ſight of <hi>God</hi> which we have by <hi>Faith</hi> doth caſt us into hope of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying <hi>God</hi> according to his promiſe, and now our ſoules<note place="margin">Pſal. 119. 81. Rom. 8. 23 Pſal. 119. 82.</note> doe faint for him and his ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; we ſigh in our ſelves waiting, and our eyes doe faile for his Word, ſaying, when wilt thou come to us and comfort us? O when ſhall I have my helpe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance from the <hi>Lord!</hi> the eye of <hi>Faith</hi> doth either actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally bring downe <hi>God</hi> into the ſoule, and is as the ſetting of the eye of a skilfull fowler up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a bird, who if he hold the bird in his eye, he will not have him long out of his hand; or actually carrie up the ſoule unto <hi>God</hi> in ſtrength of deſire, ſo that the ſoule
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:28236:24"/> cannot be in any quiet untill <hi>God</hi> be gotten and gained.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, we ſhall not be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed by the ſight of any calamities; troubles beheld without a <hi>God</hi> doe excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly damp and daunt the ſpirits of men, till <hi>Eliſhaes</hi> ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant had his eyes opened to ſee the ſtrength of Heaven, his heart was much diſmayed by the hoſte of the <hi>Syrians;</hi> but to have an eye to God in times of trouble, will prove the great upholdment of the ſoule, &amp; it is no miſerable eſtate that can diſtreſſe that man, whoſe eyes are the eyes of <hi>Faith;</hi> ſay that troopes of troubles come, and that we are to encounter with contrarieties and croſſes, even the ruffling rage of wicked me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whoſe power in ſome degree might equall their malice, yet
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:28236:24"/> ſuch a ſoule ſtands, and his heart is ſtaied within him; for he ſees more with him then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him. O the wiſedome and power which <hi>Faith</hi> doth ſee in <hi>God</hi> for the preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thoſe that are his.</p>
            <p>I reade of a <hi>Generall,</hi> who<note place="margin">Antigonus.</note> finding his ſouldiers diſmai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the ſmaleneſſe of their company and the multitudes of their enemies, asked them, but how many do you reckon mee at? who am your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander and Leader? this <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall</hi> is <hi>Faith</hi> in the ſoule, which takes off all the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quietments of our hearts un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der trouble by making men to be creatures, and ſetting <hi>God</hi> ruling in the midſt of his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, ſurely it was this eye of <hi>Faith</hi> that wrought <hi>Luther</hi> to ſuch confidence of heart in
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:28236:25"/> times of dread; for when he was told of great troubles that were like to befall him and the reſt in <hi>Germany,</hi> he made this anſwer, come, come, no matter for them all, let us ſing the forty ſixt <hi>Pſalme,</hi> and let them do their worſt: <q>ſo faith the beleevers ſoule, let men combine and conſpire to do me and the Church all the miſchiefe they can, and let things go how they will, and dangers be what they will, yet I ſee a <hi>God</hi> with me, and for me, and unto him will I looke, for by him I am ſure to be ſafe, <hi>The Lord wil be a refuge for the oppreſsed,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal 9. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>yea a refuge in time of trouble.</hi>
               </q> The Marriner is not quite de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected,<note place="margin">Simile.</note> though he ſeeth all his Sailes torne and gone, ſo long as his Anchor holds; the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:28236:25"/> Souldier is not vanquiſhed ſo ſoone as his out-workes are taken, if he be in a Caſtle or Towne of ſtrength; neither is a Chriſtian quite out of comfort and hope ſo long as<note place="margin">Zach. 9. 12.</note> he ſees his <hi>God</hi> remaining; but is a priſoner of hope tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to his ſtrong hold.</p>
            <p>Sixtly, we ſhall be feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of ſinning in times of ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities, <hi>God,</hi> ſeene by <hi>Faith</hi> is acknowledged by duty, and a mans eyes cannot be upon <hi>God</hi> at any time, but he ſhall walke with <hi>God,</hi> and tremble to ſinne againſt him; times of affliction ſhould be times of praying and of holy walking; can a man look upon <hi>God</hi> but he ſhall obſerve that <hi>God</hi> hath an eye upon him, and ſhould not Gods ſight be the great awer of the ſoule from ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning?
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:28236:26"/> to looke upon a Judge looking upon us, and to cut a purſe is the aggravation of a felonie, and to have an eye upon <hi>God</hi> in trouble, and to mingle ſinne with our ſorrow is an argument of a falſe and faithleſſe heart.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> Thirdly, this may exhort us to imitate <hi>David,</hi> O let us have our eyes to <hi>God</hi> in all our extremities, <hi>God</hi> ſaith, <hi>Looke unto mee and be ſaved,</hi> where<note place="margin">Iſa. 45. 22.</note> wee ſee, that wee can never be ſafe till we looke unto <hi>God;</hi> I know it is a very difficult, but yet it is a very uſefull and comfortable thing to have our eyes upon <hi>God</hi> in times of danger and death; the eye upon <hi>God</hi> maketh the burthen eaſie and heart lightſome; It is ſaid of the <hi>Governour</hi> of a ſhip, that he is <hi>Oculus ad coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum,</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:28236:26"/> for though in a ſtorme he hath his hand on the ſterne, yet his eye is to the pole-ſtar, &amp; it muſt be ſaid of a Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that he is <hi>Oculus ad Deum,</hi> an eye upon or unto <hi>God;</hi> O that our eyes in theſe evill times were leſſe upon the creature, and more upon <hi>God;</hi> O looke up, look up unto <hi>God</hi> the <hi>Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now that wee may with comfort practiſe this duty, I ſhall deſire you,</p>
            <p>Firſt, to get thoſe eyes which <hi>David</hi> had, wee ſhall never practiſe <hi>Davids</hi> duties without <hi>Davids</hi> graces; how can a man ſee who wants his eyes? and is it poſſible that the ſoule ſhould aſcend to <hi>God</hi> that wants <hi>Faith?</hi> ſet in for theſe eyes, a man muſt be more then nature, and reaſon, and ſence that hath his eyes
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:28236:27"/> towards <hi>God</hi> in evill times.</p>
            <p>Secondly, to get that <hi>God</hi> which <hi>David</hi> had, I tell you, that <hi>David</hi> had gotten <hi>God</hi> in his acquaintance and by way of ſpeciall intereſt, and this made him to looke upon him in an evill time; if God and wee are ſtrangers, or there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine ſtrangeneſſe twixt God and us, we ſhall never turne the eye of <hi>Faith</hi> unto him in any condition of our life; I look for help from my friend, not from a ſtranger, O ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint your ſelves with God, and then you may have your eyes upon Him.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, cloſe not with Satan in his temptations, it is the maine worke of the Divell to keepe men off from the fight of God, it is noted, that he it is that doth blinde or
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:28236:27"/> caſt duſt into the eyes of men,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 4. 4</note> interrupting, and intercepting the ſoule in all its recourſes unto God. I am certaine of this, as at all times, ſo eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in times of trouble, Satan is moſt in his darkning workes unto Chriſtians; then hee is raiſing up clouds and miſts to hinder the cleare ſights of God; now hee labours to keep downe the eye from loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king<note place="margin">Satan keepes Chriſtians from loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king up to God three vvaies.</note> up to God; O 'tis his moſt malitious work to rob a Chriſtian of his God in point of comfort and confidence, and this he doth many waies,</p>
            <p>1. Sometimes by diſgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing and diſabling God unto a Chriſtians Faith, as if that God were not able enough for ſupplies, or anſwerable to exigencies, of which if the ſoule be once perſwaded, it
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:28236:28"/> will never be drawne to look towards God in an expecting or depending way, for who will goe to an empty conduit to fetch water?</p>
            <p>2. Sometimes by diſgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing and diſabling a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans <hi>Faith</hi> unto God, for what though God be able to doe him good that lookes up unto him in evill times, yet ſaith hee, where are thine eyes? and what is thy <hi>Faith</hi> (which is ſo weake and poore) that it ſhould be able to become thine eyes to look unto God? can any man ſee that wanteth eyes? or looke ſo farre whoſe eyes are dimme?</p>
            <p>3. Sometimes hee doth over-greaten the danger, and makes men beleeve that deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance thence is impoſſible, which deſpaires the heart
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:28236:28"/> from expecting helpe from God: Now let the Divell come which way he will, we muſt not beleeve him againſt God, or follow him in his ſuggeſtions againſt a duty, but ſtill hold this concluſion, that God is never ſo darke to ſence, but <hi>Faith</hi> can ſee him, and the eyes of Faith are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo weake, but that they can thorough the darkeſt cloud and in the greateſt ſtorme, ſee an All-ſeeing and an All-hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping God, whoſe comforts are ready and ſutable for mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable and ſuffering Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, duſt not your ſelves with the duſt of the world: If men looke downe too much upon Earth, they ſhall never looke up to God in <hi>Faith,</hi> for the eye cannot
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:28236:29"/> at once looke both waies, a worldly heart is a darke heart, if the riches, and honours, and pleaſures of the world, once get into the eye of the ſoule, it is not poſſible for the ſoule to looke up unto God, can the bird flie upwards if you tie a weight upon its legg? then is it poſſible for an earthly heart to looke upon God in evill daies. I have read of<note place="margin">Duke of <hi>Alva</hi> to <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth.</note> one that was asked if hee had not obſerved the eclipſes; and his anſwer was, that hee had ſo much to doe upon Earth, that he had no leaſure to looke up to Heaven; and this I am ſure of, that an heart idolizing the creature can never be true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly depending on God, can the eye ſee its object that is full of duſt? or that ſoule looke up to God that is buryed in the creatures?</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:28236:29"/>
            <p>Fiftly, keepe the eye much in mourning for ſin; a ſight of ſin and corruption accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with godly ſorrow for the ſame, will cleare our eyes towards the comfortable ſight of God, and make us more fit to turne our eyes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him in any condition; he that cannot grieve &amp; weep for ſin, ſhall never look up to God with confidence; <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance is the turning of the ſoule from ſinne unto God,</hi> ſo that men practiſing repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance are in the right way of having their eyes towards God.</p>
            <p>Sixtly, goe to God for helpe and ſtrength unto the worke, for no man can ſee God without God, the Lord muſt take off the covering caſt over all people, and the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:28236:30"/> vaile that is ſpread over all<note place="margin">Iſa. 25. 7.</note> Nations, and vouchſafe the light of Heaven unto the ſoule, ere the ſoule can ſee him or looke unto him, and therefore let us make this prayer, <q>
                  <hi>Lord open mine eyes that I may ſee Thee, and turne mine eyes from the creatures, that I may be able to looke up unto Thee in a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending and expecting way.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>In Thee is my truſt.</head>
               <p>Heere is truſt well placed, I wounder not at the connexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of theſe two; to have eyes on God and to truſt in God: ſight is a convincing ſenſe and beſt perſwading; where wee expect good, wee dare to truſt, and no ſoule is more confident then the ſoule that
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:28236:30"/> is moſt expecting by <hi>Faith,</hi> the point intended is this,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That the truly Godly doe</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Doct.</hi> 2. Suffering times are truſting times.</note> 
                  <hi>more or leſſe truſt in God in times of calamities: ſuffering times are truſting times,</hi> here note (that by ſuffering times)<note place="margin">Suffering times what?</note> I meane times of inward and outward ſtraits wherein either a mans feares are many by reaſon of danger threatned, or a mans ſorrow is much by reaſon of miſery felt, called<note place="margin">Amos 5. 13. Pro. 15. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> in the Scripture <hi>evill times,</hi> or <hi>daies of affliction.</hi> 2. By tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting in God at ſuch times, I meane that choiſe expreſſion of <hi>Faith</hi> in applying the ſoule<note place="margin">Truſting in God what?</note> to God by an act of recum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bencie and dependance, upon the application of the word of his promiſe, take it up<note place="margin">7. Things about tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting in God.</note> thus.</p>
               <p>1. That God hath made
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:28236:31"/> over in the word of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe abundance of good and mercy, which he will vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe unto his being in and under miſery, as <hi>That he will be with them, know their ſoules in adverſity, and adminiſter both ſeaſonable and ſutable comforts unto them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2. That the truſting ſoule doth take God at his word, and cloſeth with the promiſe made, not onely by generall aſſenting, but by particular applying acts; he ſeeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and his condition in the promiſe, and makes it not onely agreeable and fitting to and for ſuch an one as hee is but withall he doth faſten up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it for himſelfe, conceiving upon good grounds that hee is the man that is ſpoken unto, and unto whom this gratious
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:28236:31"/> promiſe doth belong, this I call the ſoules putting it ſelfe into a promiſe.</p>
               <p>3. That the ſoule in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king God his truſt doth ſet God in his promiſe before it as a rock, or bottome, or foundation for upholdment and ſtaying: ſo that he is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended to be ſuch a one that will not ſuffer the ſoule to ſinke or periſh; for no man will leane upon a broken reed or ſandy foundation.</p>
               <p>4. That the maine nature of truſting in God, ſtands in the laying or hanging all a mans hopes, for helpe and comfort in evil and ſad times, upon the Lords truth for the performance of his own moſt gratious promiſe.</p>
               <p>5. (That the perſon thus truſting in God is the truly
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:28236:32"/> godly) my meaning is, that we muſt exclude all wicked and unregenerate men from this dependance and reliance on God in evill times: none but a renewed and ſanctified heart can truely truſt in God: it being a worke of grace to truſt in God; hence ſaith <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 64 10.</note> 
                  <hi>The righteous ſhall be glad in the Lord, and ſhall truſt in him,</hi> and the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 50. 10.</note> ſaith, <hi>Who is among you that feareth the Lord, that obeyeth the voice of his ſervant, that walketh in darkneſse, and hath no light? Let him truſt in the Name of the Lord, and ſtay upon his God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>6. That truſting in God is either.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Habituall.</item>
                  <item>Or,</item>
                  <item>2. Actuall.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Then doth the ſoule habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:28236:32"/> truſt in God, when it is inclining and bending to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards act of reliance; O the ſoule is willing to reſt it ſelfe, and hath a conſtant diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in it to ſtay it ſelfe upon God, even when it is not able actually to exerciſe its truſting upon God in that way and meaſure it would and ſhould; but take me a Chriſtian at the worſt and loweſt, and wee may affirme of him, that hee doth habitually truſt in God.</p>
               <p>7. That the godly man doth truſt in God 3. wayes, 1. Only, <hi>In thee is my truſt,</hi> ſaith <hi>David,</hi> not in men as God, nor in men with God, but in God alone. 2. Wholy, the all, even the might and the truth of their confidence is caſt upon God. 3. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:28236:33"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:28236:33"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:28236:34"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:28236:34"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:28236:35"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:28236:35"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:28236:36"/> at all times and in all conditions doe they rely upon God, though chiefely and moſtly in evill and ſad times.</p>
               <p>Now this they doe upon<note place="margin">4 Grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on God.</note> theſe 4. grounds.</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>Virtute praecepti,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that God doth call for, and require their truſting in Him; the commands are ſo many that I ſhall ſave my la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to quote the Scriptures.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>ratione pacti,</hi> becauſe God in the covenant hath made over himſelfe to be <hi>Sunne</hi> and <hi>ſhield, rock</hi> and <hi>tower</hi> of defence, yea and an houſe of fortreſſes unto his, and one every way All-ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient for the defence and ſafety of his, ſo that there is no danger ſo great and imminent from which his power is not
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:28236:36"/> able to reſcue his; as he can hurt and ſpoile all the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches enemies, blaſting their power and defeating their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie, ſo he can ſhelter his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his wings, becomming their ſafety and ſecurity, he is the hill of helpe and moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine for ſafety, it is the <hi>Peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſis</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 65. 5.</note> of God to be the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence of all the ends of the Earth: and <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>God</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 46. 1. expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</note> 
                  <hi>is our refuge and ſtrength, a very preſent helpe in trouble:</hi> Marke well the place, 1. <hi>God is a refuge,</hi> where the alluſion is to thoſe Citties of refuge unto which a perſon that had ſlaine a man at unawares was to flie, where he was ſecure and ſafe from the purſuer, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timating unto us, that if dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and troubles doe purſue Chriſtians at the heeles, yet
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:28236:37"/> God would be their hiding and ſecuring place from all: 2. <hi>God is a ſtrength,</hi> it may be the power of dangers and troubles may be great, now if the refuge want ſtrength, a mans ſecurity cannot be much, but God is Almighty, and ſuch ſtrength unto his that no ſtrength ſhall over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come them, untill it can over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come him. 3. <hi>God is a helpe,</hi> he doth not ſtand by looking on his in their troubles, and ſuffering them to be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come by their owne weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but will put forth his ſtrength and aſſiſtance, bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring all their burdens for them, and enabling them to ſtand under all. 4. <hi>God is a preſent helpe in time of need:</hi> that is, let dangers be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, God will not be abſent,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:28236:37"/> neither will He delay his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence for his, or come in with the ſame when it is too late; ſo that this Text doth ſhew that He is unqueſtionably ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for the ſafety of his, which muſt needs bee the ground of confidence; for the ſoule doth betake it ſelfe alone to ſtrength; according<note place="margin">Pro. 18. 10 Pſal. 18. 1, 2. 28. 7. 3.</note> to that of <hi>Salomon, The name of the Lord is a ſtrong tower, the righteous runne into it and are ſafe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>3. Thirdly, <hi>ratione facti:</hi> becauſe God is truſty, and ſuch a one that never faileth them that place their truſt in<note place="margin">Pſal. 22. 4, 5.</note> Him: <hi>Our Fathers truſted in thee, they trusted and thou did<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt deliver them, they cried un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, and were delivered: they truſted in thee and were not confounded.</hi> The meaning is
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:28236:38"/> this; that there care was in evill times to truſt in the Lord, and God did not deceive their truſt, but made it to be their ſafety; <hi>Ahas</hi> made the King<note place="margin">2 Chron. 28. 20. Iſa. 30. 1.</note> of <hi>Aſsiria</hi> his refuge, but he was not his ſtrength; <hi>Iſraell</hi> went downe to <hi>Egypt</hi> for helpe, and truſted in Charets and Horſe-men, but they were not holpen; but who ſo come unto God by way of dependance, are ſure to finde this made good, <hi>I will not faile thee nor for ſake thee.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 13. 5.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, <hi>ratione fidei:</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe upon them is beſtowed the grace of <hi>Faith,</hi> which is a truſting grace, a relying grace, full of fiduciall acts, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver more active upon God then in hard times, and times of dangers; the Prophet ſaith,<note place="margin">Heb. 2. 4. opened.</note> 
                  <hi>The juſt ſhall live by Faith,</hi>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:28236:38"/> which place wee thus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound, the Prophet had fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told of ſad times to come up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Church; Now upon the hearing of this, it became a great queſtion, but how ſhall the juſt doe in ſuch times? The anſwer is, hee ſhall live by <hi>Faith,</hi> God hath given him the grace of <hi>Faith,</hi> which now he ſhall exerciſe, by putting himſelfe under Gods wing, and making God his tower of ſafety: when others ſhall live either by their wits and ſhifts, or by their feares and fence, the truly godly ſhall ſubſiſt by their beleeving dependance on God: ſurely they that doe beleeve in God cannot but truſt in God: to apply the point, note 3. things.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label> Firſt, That there is a wide
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:28236:39"/> difference betweene the<note place="margin">Differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce betweene godly and wicked men in truſting God.</note> childe of God and wicked men in times of extremitie and trouble: I deny not but the ſame calamitous condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may befall them both, God may and doth caſt both the one and the other into ſad and fearing times, but the thing I aime at is this, that the carriage of the one and the other is not the ſame in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of confidence in God; there are 3. things incident<note place="margin">3. Things incident to wicked men in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill times. 1. To have no place for confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. Pro. 30. 26</note> to wicked men in evill times.</p>
               <p>1. Either they have no place for confidence, but run up and downe crying, <hi>Who will ſhew us any good?</hi> they are worſe then the poore ſilly creatures, who in times of danger have their retyring places; the poore <hi>Conies a feeble folke, yet make they their
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:28236:39"/> houſe in the rocks, the rocks are</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal 104. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>a refuge to the Conies;</hi> theſe creatures can burrow them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the rocke when they are in danger of Doggs; the Birds have neſts wherein they hide themſelves when dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers approach, hence <hi>Moab</hi> is adviſed to bee like <hi>the Dove,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jer. 48, 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>that maketh her neſt in the ſide of the holes mouth,</hi> there ſhee will neſtle her ſelfe, when ſhee is purſued by the Birds of prey; but a wicked carnall man when troubles come, lies o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to all winds, and is like unto a ſhip whoſe tacklings are broken, and Anchor loſt, toſſed up and downe, and hurried from place to place, till at length ſhe ſuffer ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke; or as a <hi>Meteor</hi> that hangs in the clouds, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tell which way to fall;
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:28236:40"/> Oh how are wicked men ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed with feares and cares, and pulled in pieces with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractions? Oh how diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, hopeleſſe and helpeleſſe are they, and even at their wits end, when dangers are threatned or preſent.</p>
               <p>2. They miſplace their<note place="margin">2. To miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>place their confide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.</note> confidence, they cannot ſay in thee O Lord is my truſt, but O God my truſt is in men and meanes; That I may not<note place="margin">A caution about the uſe of meàes for ſafety.</note> be miſtaken, know, that I doe not ſpeake againſt the uſe of lawfull meanes, or outward helpes for our ſafety in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous times, but this is the worke of wicked men to Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lize the meanes, and by them to rob God of that truſt that<note place="margin">Wicked mens con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence lies</note> is due to him, what is more uſuall with them, then to put truſt in places; if in times of<note place="margin">1. In pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</note>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:28236:40"/> feares and dangers they can but get into a ſtrong Citty and a well built Tower or Caſtle, now with the men of <hi>Tyrus</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ezek. 27. 11.</note> they are ſafe enough, that ſhall be their God, and all their ſafety ſhall depend upon it; if their confidence lye not in this, then it may be it is in men and munition, wherein<note place="margin">2. In mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition and men. Pſal. 20. 7.</note> the arme of fleſh is relyed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: <hi>Some truſt in Horſes and ſome in Chariots,</hi> forgetting that an Horſe is a vaine thing for ſafety. Others place their confidence in their riches and<note place="margin">3. In weal th and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours. Pro. 18. 11</note> honours; <hi>The rich mans wealth is his ſtrong Citty, and as an high wall in his conceit,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon, And they ſet their neſts on high that they may be</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hab. 2. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>delivered from the power of evill,</hi> ſaith the Prophet <hi>Habbacock.</hi> O ſay they, were it not that
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:28236:41"/> we were wealthy, and known to be ſo, and had we not high places, then wee might feare gun-ſhot, and thinke our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves in dangers: others run a little higher in their vaine confidence, and doe truſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their Church priviledges,<note place="margin">4. In Church priviled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. Ier. 7. 4.</note> like thoſe in <hi>Ieremiahs</hi> dayes, who cried out <hi>the Temple of the Lord, the Temple of the Lord:</hi> they doe thinke be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they have the Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of God amongſt them, that theſe ſhall be a refuge unto them, which the Holy Ghoſt calls <hi>a truſting in lying words,</hi> theſe and other the like confidences are vaine confidences; for all ſtrong holds if truſted unto, ſhall be like <hi>Figg-trees with the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Nah. 3. 12 Zephan. 1 18.</note> 
                  <hi>firſt ripe figgs,</hi> and it is <hi>nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſilver or gold that ſhall be
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:28236:41"/> able to deliver them in the day</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſa. 29. 1, 2</note> 
                  <hi>of the Lords wrath, and Ariell it ſelfe ſhall be diſtreſsed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>3. Or they ſhall fall away<note place="margin">3. Forſake the Lord for their confidence Jer. 2. 11.</note> from the Lord, ſlighting and rejecting his helpe in evill times, <hi>Saul</hi> went to the witch, and the Prince would attend no longer upon the Lord, and wicked men forſake the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of living water; ſurely ſuch as fall from God doe not depend on God, unleſſe you will ſay, that hee doth lay himſelfe upon the fountaine or rock, that caſts himſelfe from the rocke into the Sea; but to leave them to the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie of miſeries, and to inherit their folly.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>2</label> Secondly, this may teach us to ſound our owne tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers,<note place="margin">Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> whether that wee are truſting Chriſtians in evill and
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:28236:42"/> dangerous times, can we ſay with <hi>David, In thee is my truſt?</hi> then theſe 6. things<note place="margin">6. Signes of men that truſt in God in evill times 1. Care to pleaſe God.</note> will be more or leſſe found upon us.</p>
               <p>1. Our care will bee to pleaſe God in all things: him upon whom we depend wee will ſtudie to content; a child feares to diſpleaſe his Father, and a Tennant feares to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe his Landlord, becauſe of their dependance on them, and ſurely if wee doe truſt in God, we will covet to walke in all well pleaſing unto God, ſhunning whatſoever way or courſe is contrary or grieving to him: None but a mad-man would offend his defence: ſhall God defend us, and ſhall we offend Him? That ſoule doth looke for very lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle good from God that is
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:28236:42"/> careleſſe of his praiſe and pleaſing.</p>
               <p>2. We ſhall make up our<note place="margin">2. Making God a por<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion to us</note> ſelves in God in all conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: the heart doth chuſe that thing for its portion, which it maketh to be its confidence; <hi>The Lord is my</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lam. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 24</note> 
                  <hi>portion, therefore will I hope in him,</hi> ſaith the Church, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon is it that the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſaith, <hi>Whom have I in Heaven but thee? and there is none upon</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 73. 25, 26.</note> 
                  <hi>Earth that I deſire beſides thee, my fleſh and my heart faileth, but God is the rock of my heart and my portion for ever:</hi> Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly God is heritage and porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on enough to that ſoule that truſteth in him; the ſoule that relies upon him, ſhall finde him to be a full and ſutable good unto it ſelfe, and can ſee that it hath no reaſon to
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:28236:43"/> looke out of God for ſupplies and ſufficiencies.</p>
               <p>3. We ſhall uſe the meanes for ſafety, but leave the iſſue to God: ſuch as truſt in God will not tempt God, but ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply themſelves to the wiſe and carefull uſe of all thoſe meanes which ſerve God in his care and providence over them. <hi>Iacob</hi> truſted God for deliverance, and ſo did <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> and yet they did not neglect or flie over the meanes for their ſuccour and ſafety in evill times, the one ſends preſents and marſhalls<note place="margin">Gen. 32.</note> his family, the ſecond abides in ſtrong holds in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 23.</note> and the laſt ſtaies in the ſhip and keepes the Marriners<note place="margin">Acts 27.</note> with him; hee that truſts a Phyſitions skill will be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to obſerve what is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:28236:43"/> to him, and as meanes are to be uſed, ſo when meanes are uſed, wee ſhall truſt God with the iſſue, and unto God for the ſucceſſe; <hi>it is pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſumption not truſt to ſever the meanes from the end, it is feare not Faith to uſe meanes, and yet to vexe our ſoules about the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe:</hi> ſuch as truſt God doe chiefly commit the iſſue of all the meanes they doe uſe unto God: knowing that it is mans worke to uſe the meanes, and Gods to bring about the ſucceſſe.<note place="margin">4. Living by Faith in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> outward meanes faile.</note>
               </p>
               <p>4. Wee ſhall live by <hi>Faith</hi> in the promiſes when out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward meanes for comfort and deliverance are wanting, a politician will truſt as farre as reaſon can carry him, and a naturall man will truſt as farre as his ſences lead him; if ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:28236:44"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:28236:44"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:28236:45"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:28236:45"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:28236:46"/> can ſee reaſons for, or waies and meanes of delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and ſafety before them, they can and will truſt in God, els they fall downe or fall off, whereas ſuch as tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly truſt in God, will and can (in ſome meaſure) reſt on the bare word and naked pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of God, even then when they can ſee no meanes before them, but that the preſent face and ſtate of things doe ſeeme altogether contrary unto them; <hi>Though the Lord kill</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Job 15. 13</note> 
                  <hi>mee yet will I trust in him,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſa. 50. 10</note> ſaith <hi>Iob:</hi> and the command is, when that wee are in darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and can ſee no light, even in ſuch an eſtate to truſt in God: a child in the darke takes hold of his Father, and a Chriſtian without meanes will truſt in his God, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:28236:46"/> that God is all meanes in himſelfe, and that hee can do things for his Churches good and comfort, when all outward meanes doth threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the contrary.</p>
               <p>5. Wee ſhall truſt <hi>God</hi>
                  <note place="margin">5. Tru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſting of God.</note> withall: they that doe truſt in <hi>God,</hi> will alſo truſt <hi>God,</hi> as knowing that the ſafety and ſecurity of all is in <hi>God;</hi> tell mee now, doe you truſt <hi>God</hi> with your names, eſtates, callings, poſterities, bodies and ſoules? doe you truſt your temporall and eternall eſtate in <hi>Gods</hi> hand, ſo that you can ſay, <q>I have nothing in mine owne keeping, I dare not ſo much as to truſt my ſelfe with my ſelfe, or any thing I have with any other creature, but all is committed by mee to the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:28236:47"/> Lord, whom I know to be faithfull;</q> this is an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that the ſoule doth truſt in the Lord: <hi>I know whom I have beleeved, I am</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Tim. 1. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>perſwaded that hee is able to keepe that which I have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted unto him againſt that day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, wee ſhall have a<note place="margin">6. Quiet and reſt of ſoule.</note> ground for reſt and quiet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our ſoules: Truſt in <hi>God</hi> doth 1. Bottome the ſoule ſtrongly, ſo that there ſhall be a ſtaying of murmurings and grudgings ariſing within the Soule. 2. Supply the ſoule with a greater ground of quiet and comfort, then there can be cauſes of feare and troubling; <hi>God</hi> is a Center for reſt, and a quiet Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſo that the ſoule can never be at reſt untill that it
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:28236:47"/> come to reſt upon him: It is the worke of truſt to caſt the ſoule into a fixing and ſetling condition: I doe not ſay that the truſting ſoule is totally freed from ſtirrings and ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings even in evill times; I<note place="margin">A truſting ſoule is a quiet ſoule and hovv?</note> know that our fleſh which we carry about us is full of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections, and daily troubles us in our quiet, but yet know, that though feares may mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rially riſe in a truſting heart, yet they doe not victoriou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly worke in that ſoule that is truly truſting; the promiſe is, <hi>Thou wilt keepe him in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſa. 26. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>peace whoſe minde is ſtaied on thee, becauſe hee truſteth in thee;</hi> and againe, <hi>They that</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal 125. 1</note> 
                  <hi>truſt in the Lord ſhall be as mount Zion which cannot be moved;</hi> and againe, <hi>He ſhall</hi>
                  <note place="margin">112. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>not be afraid of evill tidings,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:28236:48"/> his heart is fixed trusting in the Lord.</hi> Hence was it that <hi>David</hi> finding a mutinie with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in<note place="margin">43. ult.</note> his ſoule, hee takes up the contention by charging his ſoule <hi>to truſt in God;</hi> O when other mens ſoules are under confuſion and reſtleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and moving within them, <hi>As the trees of the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſa. 7. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>wood are mooved with the winde,</hi> becauſe they are hard beſtead, when feares and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors doe rack and rend their hearts in pieces, and all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they truſt not in <hi>God,</hi> then the ſoule whoſe truſt is in the Lord, hath quiet in ſpirit, and he ſaith, <hi>Why ſhould</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 49. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>I feare in the daies of evill?</hi> hee then ſings over the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſixe Pſalme with holy <hi>Luther.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> Thirdly, wee ſhould ſtrive
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:28236:48"/> to attaine to <hi>Davids</hi> pitch, and endeavour to be ſuch that can truly ſay, <hi>In thee is</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 57. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>my truſt,</hi> or as in another Pſalme, <hi>My ſoule truſteth in thee.</hi> Thus to doe is very ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary and comfortable, but yet of great difficulty; it is a hard thing to bring the heart from creature confidence un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to divine confidence, that a ſoule ſhould be beſet with miſery, and apprehend no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but ſtormes and threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of deſtruction, and yet now to ſtay it ſelfe upon <hi>God,</hi> in whoſe hand the cloud and calamity is, is a worke both above, and againſt nature, which that wee may be brought unto, I will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound theſe ſix helpes.</p>
               <p>Firſt, you muſt goe to<note place="margin">Six helpes to truſting in God.</note> Schoole to learne <hi>Gods</hi> name
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:28236:49"/> aright, <hi>They that know thy</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 9. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>Name will put their truſt in thee,</hi> ſaith <hi>David:</hi> and in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Pſalme hee ſaith, <hi>How excellent is thy loving kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 36. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>O God! therefore the children of men put their truſt under the ſhadow of thy wings,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now the name of <hi>God</hi> is<note place="margin">The name of God what?</note> the Lords revelation of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in his Word, and it doth comprehend under it all the glorious Attributes of <hi>God,</hi> together with the promiſes of grace and mercy which he hath made unto his<note place="margin">The know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Gods name what?</note> Church, and the knowledge of that name is no more then the informing our mindes and underſtandings in the truth and meaning of <hi>God</hi> in all his glorious Attributes, and gratious promiſes, ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:28236:49"/> if the ſoule did once come to apprehend <hi>God</hi> aright in the Attributes of his Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, Power, Mercy and Providence, and to looke upon all the promiſes as ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute truths, and full of goodneſſe, it would not but be drawne into truſt and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence; <hi>God</hi> ſaith in one Pſalme, <hi>I will ſet him on</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 91. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>high becauſe hee hath knowne my Name,</hi> the meaning is, I will ſee he ſhall be ſafe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he hath truſted in mee; where we ſee that the very<note place="margin">Truſting in God called the knowing of Gods name and why?</note> truſting in <hi>God</hi> is called by the knowing of <hi>Gods</hi> name, and why ſo? 1. Becauſe in truſting we gaine an experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall knowledge of <hi>Gods</hi> name. 2. Becauſe by know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his name we come to the truſting in his name, will
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:28236:50"/> any man truſt in him whom hee doth not know? ſurely <hi>God</hi> unknowne can never be relied upon; I muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore make it my worke not onely to know there is a <hi>God,</hi> which is to know him by name; but I muſt know him in his ſufficiencie of ſtrength for ſafety and defence, and as one that will gratiouſly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit mee into his protection, I recourſing unto him in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and <hi>Faith,</hi> if ever my ſoule ſhall draw into him in a way of confidence and dependance.</p>
               <p>Secondly, get a friendly<note place="margin">2. To get acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with God.</note> and familiar acquaintance with <hi>God,</hi> as ignorance ſo ſtrangeneſſe cannot rely upon God, and it is not every ordinary acquaintance with God, but a ſpeciall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:28236:50"/> with him that doth breed a dependance on him; A man muſt know <hi>God</hi> by way of tryall ere hee will truſt him, and a man<note place="margin">Speciall acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with God what?</note> muſt have ſpeciall intimacie with <hi>God,</hi> ſo as to ſee him a reconciled <hi>God</hi> unto him in the face of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> ere he can bring his heart to truſt in him; I ſay if a man can ſee <hi>God</hi> as his Father and beſt friend, even one twixt him and whom there are no quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels and differences, he ſhall with much cheerefullneſſe of heart relie upon him.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, ſet up <hi>Faith</hi> into<note place="margin">3. Set up Faith, into exerciſe and life.</note> exerciſe; the grace of <hi>Faith</hi> muſt not onely live in us, but we muſt alſo live by it, if ever wee intend truly to truſt in <hi>God,</hi> the life of ſence weakens our dependance on God; the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:28236:51"/> life of reaſon ſets up our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance on the creatures, but the life of <hi>Faith</hi> doth quicken and raiſe up a ſtrong dependance on God, this is <hi>the dwelling in the ſecret of the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 91. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>most high,</hi> and the ſhutting up of the ſoule within the<note place="margin">Eſa. 26. 20</note> doores of the divine cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers.</p>
               <p>I conceive thus much of the life of <hi>Faith;</hi> 1. It will make God that unto us which our neceſſities doe require him to be; even a rock, and Tower, refuge and fortreſſe, <hi>Becauſe thou haſt made the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 91. 9, 10.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord which is my reſuge thine habitation, there ſhall no evill befall thee,</hi> where we ſee that <hi>Faith</hi> in working makes God an habitation. 2. It will draw home the particular and the generall promiſes of
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:28236:51"/> ſafety unto a mans ſelfe in particular: Now the ſetling of the promiſes on the ſoule is the way to bring in a man unto dependance; for it doth let in or enter a man into the goodneſſe of God, hence<note place="margin">Pſal. 119 114.</note> ſaith <hi>David, Thou art my hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding place and my ſhield, I hope in thy Word,</hi> where we ſee that <hi>David</hi> did make God his hiding place by hoping in his Word. 3. It will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>title a man unto <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> in whom all the promiſes are yea and Amen: The way to come into God is <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> and God is no farther an hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding place to the perſon of any man, then he is united to Chriſt by <hi>Faith;</hi> It is Chriſt that makes God our Shield and Tower, and ſo as Faith doth worke it ſelfe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:28236:52"/> Chriſt, it doth worke the ſoule upon God, for I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not faſten my ſelfe upon God, but in and by the <hi>Mediatour</hi> upon whom my <hi>Faith</hi> is pitched.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, leane not unto<note place="margin">4. The gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving over a mans ſelfe. Pro. 3. 5.</note> ſelfe-policie and ſelfe-power: hence ſaith <hi>Salomon, Truſt in the Lord with all thine heart, and leane not to thine owne underſtanding,</hi> ſurely wee muſt empty our ſelves of our ſelves, if ever wee will be brought to truſt upon God, what man will be beholding to another ſo as to ſeeke unto him and to caſt himſelfe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, if he conceive him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be ſelfe-ſufficient? and ſurely this is mans proud diſpoſition, that he will be as little beholding to God for any thing as he can, for hee
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:28236:52"/> will try his owne wits, and parts and friends in the firſt place, and if hee finde in them reliefe, then hee will ſtick and ſtay; wee ſee in experience, that no man commits his body to the<note place="margin">Simile.</note> water till he finde no ground for his feete to faſten upon; ſo that there is a great deale of neceſſity for a man to denie himſelfe, and to give over himſelfe, if ever he intend a dependance upon his God, at any time, for any thing.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, caſt off the way and<note place="margin">5. The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of the vvay of ſin. Iob 22. 24, 25.</note> courſe of ſinne and propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe by timely and ſerious repentance, <hi>If thou returne to the Almighty thou ſhalt bee built up, thou ſhalt put away in iquity farre from thy tabernacle, then ſhalt thou lay up gold as duſt, and the gold of Ophir as
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:28236:53"/> the stones of the brookes: yea the Almighty ſhall be thy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence,</hi> how can a man expect ſafety from God, when hee walkes in a courſe contrary unto God; can ſuch imagine God will be the protection of their perſons, who are the provocation of his eyes; ſure I am, this is the fruite of a life led in ſinne, to keepe off the ſoule from comming in unto God by way of duty and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance, I ſay, that the love and life of ſinne doth dead and damp the heart in all mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and actions unto God, and therefore it muſt be your worke, to purge your heart from all the love of ſinne, and ſtudy the way of giving o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the ſlaviſh ſervice of ſinne, and then the way is open to God; the God on whom we
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:28236:53"/> ſtay our ſelves, is an holy God, and wee muſt reſolve to be holy and reformed per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; <hi>they ſhall call themſelves</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 48. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>the holy City, and ſtay them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves upon the God of Iſrael.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>6. Laſtly, ſettle all ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies<note place="margin">6. Setting all ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſuccours in God.</note> upon God; what wee truſt upon, we muſt make all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient unto us, now if wee have this skill to make God anſwerable to all our exigen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and if wee can ſee that wee cannot need or deſire that thing that is not to be found in him in an overflowing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance, it would mightily enable us to make him our truſt: ſuch who attribute too much to the ſtreame, and take from the fullneſſe of the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, will never make their recourſes to the fountaine. Oh we have a full God, who is
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:28236:54"/> Sun and ſhield, and excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding great reward unto all thoſe that come in unto Him, and will never leave the ſoule deſtitute, which doth depend upon Him: which is the thing <hi>David</hi> deſireth, and is the laſt part,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Leave not my ſoule deſtitute.</head>
               <p>Here is the true conſequent of beleeving confidence, it makes a man to flie to God by prayer, notwithſtanding all troubles; ſurely wee cannot<note place="margin">1. Truſt in God &amp; praying to God are undivided co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panions Pſal. 62. 8</note> well divide the act of Faith from the exerciſe of Prayer, <hi>David</hi> in one Pſalme by way of counſell faith, <hi>truſt in him alwayes ye people, and powre out your hearts before him;</hi> and here he is upon the practiſe of his owne Doctrine, <hi>In thee is
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:28236:54"/> my truſt, leave not my ſoule deſtitute:</hi> intimating unto us a true triall of our truſting in God; it is then right and ſound when it puts on the ſoule to prayer, he doth truſt beſt in God, that doth pray moſt to God, a praying heart is an evidence of a truſting heart.</p>
               <p>2. We muſt not divide the<note place="margin">2. Times of trouble ought to be times of prayer.</note> practiſe of prayer from times of troubles; troublous times are praying times; then or ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſhould Chriſtians beſet the Lord with requeſts, and powre out their ſoules unto Him; 1. the command is, <hi>Call</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſ. 50. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>upon me in the day of trouble,</hi> and<note place="margin">Jam. 5. 13</note> 
                  <hi>is any man afflicted let him pray. 2. David</hi> under his feares, and in the midſt of his troubles beſought the Lord. 3. And the promiſe is, that <hi>whoſoever
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:28236:55"/> ſhall call upon the name of the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joel. 2. 32.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord ſhall be delivered:</hi> I am ſure that <hi>Iacob</hi> applied him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to this practiſe, and it prooved prevailing; <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>
                  </label> Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans muſt learne to pray, as well as to truſt in God, or elſe their truſt will faile them; I conceive we doe put forth our confidence in praying; O that we were more in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and that wee would lift up our hearts in praying unto our God, this ſhould ſhelter us, and chaſe away feared dangers: a volley of Prayers ſent up morning and evening to Heaven, will doe a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and Citie more good, then all the munition in the world. A praying people have beene the terrour of ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and the ſafeguard of <hi>Nations;</hi> Prayers is the moſt
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:28236:55"/> efficatious engine, making way for the good and ſafety of the <hi>Church</hi> in all Ages, when all policies and power have beene at a ſtand, this hath made way for peace and ſafety; This, this is the little great thing that hath overtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned all plots, blaſted all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracies, and withſtood all oppoſitions, it weaknes ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and encreaſeth friends, by ruling God, and over-ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling men: hee wants not Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of proofe in his houſe that hath a praying ſpirit in his breſt; I conceive, did we pray more, wee ſhould feare leſſe, for that which is our victory with God ſhall be our conqueſt over men, <hi>Thou haſt</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 32. 28.</note> 
                  <hi>prevailed with God, thou ſhalt alſo prevaile with men,</hi> ſaith God to <hi>Iacob:</hi> I beſeech<note place="margin">Job. 15. 4.</note>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:28236:56"/> you that you would be ſo<note place="margin">Iob 15. 4.</note> farre from reſtraining Prayer before God, that you make it your daily worke to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the name of the Lord, ſtill crying unto Him and calling upon Him, adding this to your practiſe, which was the<note place="margin">Iames 5. 17. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> commendation of <hi>Elias,</hi> that you pray in your praying.</p>
               <p>But come wee now more narrowly to the matter of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> prayer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Leave not my ſoule deſtitute,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">4. Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations in the words. 1. The poſſibility of having a ſoule left deſtitute.</note>
               </p>
               <p>That is bare and forſaken of divine helpe and comfort; Whence we Whence we learne firſt, <hi>The poſsibility of having the ſoule of a Chriſtian left naked and bare of divine grace, comfort and aſsiſtance,</hi> there may not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be a withdrawing of an outwardly ſupplying and upholding good, but of an
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:28236:56"/> inwardly comforting and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious preſence, though the Lord doth not totally deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute and finally deſert the ſoules of his, yet comforts and ſupports may for a long time and in a great degree be withdrawne; <hi>Sion</hi> ſaid, <hi>The</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſa. 49. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord hath forgotten mee: Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 70. 5. 25. 16.</note> is poore and needy in one Pſalme, and deſolate and afflicted in another; Alas! how many of Gods deare ones doe find this to be true, that to their ſeeming, their God is gone, and comfort gone, and there is none to owne them, and ſtand by them: <hi>There is none to helpe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 22. 11</note> ſaith <hi>David.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, the miſery of a<note place="margin">2. It is a miſery to be left de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute.</note> divinely deſtitute and deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſoule; ſuch a ſoule is a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable ſoule, and the miſery
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:28236:57"/> of this condition, makes <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> to deprecate it, the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of a good temper doth not make the body more mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable, nor the withdrawing of the Sunne the night to be more darke, then the leaving the ſoule deſtitute in divine reſpects doth make the ſoule ſad and miſerable: 'Tis mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery to be under miſery, but in times of miſery to be left unto miſery, by Gods with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing of himſelfe from a man, makes the miſery over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſerable: For a lame man to fall it's miſery, but when hee is downe to have his crut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches taken from him, and all to forſake him, it's the leaving of him in miſery.<note place="margin">It is a mercy to finde di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour in miſery.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſer. </seg>3</label> Thirdly, That it is a great mercy to bee followed with ſpirituall ſuccours, and divine
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:28236:57"/> ſupplies in times of miſery, this is eaſing to the ſpirit, and the burthen will be the better borne and endured; this is chearing and reviving: the ſpirit will not ſoone ſinke and faint under any trouble whilſt God is with it, and all its com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts are about it; the woe is to him that is alone.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſer. </seg>4</label> Fourthly, that the inſtant and conſtant deſire of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian<note place="margin">Divine aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance &amp; preſence is to be ſought.</note> ſhould bee after divine aſſiſtance in troubles. 1. A man ſhall never need a God more in company and comfort, then when he is in, and under trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, if all the creatures leave us (as they may) yet till God leave us wee ſhall never be deſtitute; for God is all in all, for the reliefe of that ſoule with whom hee is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent: beſides, 2. the ſoule
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:28236:58"/> hath many pretious promiſes for divine ſupply and ſuccour in evills, and therefore hee may be the more bold to put up his requeſt to God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Leave not my ſoule deſtitute.</head>
               <p>To conclude the whole.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label> Firſt, I pitty ſuch men who are forſaken and deſtitute men, ſuch whom Sathan hath bereaved of their comforts, God denies his grace unto, or withdrawes the influence of his comfort from; A deſolate Widdow forſaken of friends, a brave Commander deſtitute of men and munition, and a ſoule left by God in miſery, are equally miſerable.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>2</label> Secondly, We learne, that men deſtitute of God, are the moſt helpeleſſe creatures un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:28236:58"/> Heaven, ſuch ſhall doe God, the King and the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, little good ſervice, that have Feathers in their hatts, Armour on their backs, and Weapons in their hands, wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Grace in their hearts; though their oathes may be many, and violence great, yet their ſtrength is ſmall, for they are deſtitute and deſerted perſons.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>3</label> Thirdly, In the middeſt of our dangers, let us labour to keepe God with us and about us, if we make him our friend wee need not feare who is our enemy, and God ſupplying us wee have ſtrength enough, and ſhall finde comfort enough in the midſt of dangers and death it ſelfe. <g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="narration">
            <pb facs="tcp:28236:59"/>
            <pb n="89" facs="tcp:28236:59"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Narration of the</hi> vertuous Life and happy Death of Miſtriſſe <hi>Iulian Blackwell.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>EE are this day<note place="margin">The Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication to the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion.</note> met, according to the practiſe of the Saints in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to performe a duty, and pay a debt to the remainder of our Chriſtian Siſter Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriſſe <hi>Iulian Blackwell,</hi> which is now to be laid with honour in her grave, as into a houſe of ſafe cuſtody, and bed of reſt, to remaine there untill the
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:28236:60"/> reſurrection; And finding this to be the practiſe of ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable<note place="margin">Cent. Mag. 4. c. 6. p. 45 5.</note> antiquity, to cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate the Funerals of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, with the mentioning of their juſt praiſes, you muſt give mee leave (treading in<note place="margin">Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium dabo veritati non amici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae. Ber.</note> their paths) to give teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny unto the truth, in ſpeaking of her gratious diſpoſition, and vertuous converſation; onely take two things along<note place="margin">Securius &amp; ſincee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius viſa ſolent quam audita nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rari Goff. vit. Bern. lib 1. pre ceſ.</note> with you; Firſt, that I intend to ſpeake no more of her then what mine owne knowledge and obſervation doth leade mee unto. Secondly, that my aime in this Worke is, to moderate the grieving ſpirits of thoſe that were neere un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her, whoſe loſſe is great; and to yeeld unto you all mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of good inſtruction and Chriſtian imitation, ſeeing
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:28236:60"/> you know not how ſoone her condition may be yours.</p>
            <p>And here paſſing over her deſcent, leaving that to the Heralds; I might begin with her curteſie, modeſtie, and gravity in her outward courſe and carriage, in which ſhee did ſo ſhine, that ſhee wonne much love from all ſuch who well knew her, and were themſelves lovers of a cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous and ſober converſation: Next I might lay downe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you, her fidelity, and love to her loving Husband, with whom ſhee lived in an unſpotted way, avoiding that lightneſſe, and looſeneſſe, which is too too notorious and ſhamefull in many of her Sexe.</p>
            <p>I might alſo further diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of her tenderneſſe, and
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:28236:61"/> love unto her children, to whom ſhee ſhewed her ſelfe a Mother indeed, by ſeeking their good in the beſt things, and furthering them to her power in the waies of holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>But leaving theſe, there<note place="margin">10. Things in her.</note> are ten things which I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve as notable in her, and worthy all our imitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>Firſt, God had made her<note place="margin">1. Tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of heart ſeene in foure things.</note> a Chriſtian of a very tender heart, and ſenſible ſpirit; as her naturall diſpoſition was ſoftly, ſo ſhee had a ſpirituall diſpoſition of ſoftneſſe: there were foure waies by which her tenderneſſe of Spirit did appeare.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Shee was apprehenſive<note place="margin">1. Senſe of ſin.</note> and feeling of ſins working and burden; the body of
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:28236:61"/> ſinne which ſhee did beare about her, as a body with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in her body, ſhee made ſuch a body of death unto her, that with teares ſhee would often complaine to my ſelfe and others, of her wretchedneſſe and weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomeneſſe under the ſame; a bleſſed temper, and argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſpirituall life, to find and feele the contrary workings of ſinfull cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption unto the workings of grace within the ſoule.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Shee was ſenſible of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans<note place="margin">2. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tations.</note> temptations, and his ſtrong workings againſt her graces and her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts; Satan was her ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary, and ſhee knew what it was to have Satan to be her adverſary; (ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if God be a mans friend,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:28236:62"/> Satan will be his enemy, and who ſo have tender and gratious ſpirits, they cannot but be more or leſſe ſenſible of Satans workings againſt them:) Satan did ſo often and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly diſquiet her, that ſhee feared leaſt ſhee ſhould at the laſt be overcome by him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Shee had a ſympathi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing<note place="margin">3. Sympa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy.</note> ſpirit; feeling the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent conditions of the members of the myſticall body, whether in miſery or in comfort; if the Church and Chriſtians did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce; ſhee rejoyced alſo; if they were in ſadneſſe, ſhee was in heavineſſe; in which practiſe ſhee ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her ſelfe a right living member; and I could wiſh
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:28236:62"/> that there were not the fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of bowels this way amongſt too too many of us. What a ſhame is it unto us, that Churches abroad are bleeding, and many Chriſtians at home in miſery and dying, and yet none in compariſon do regard or feele the ſame.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Shee had an undigeſting<note place="margin">4 Riſings againſt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</note> ſpirit; I meane a ſpirit that was full of painefull gratings at the ſight of ſinfull objects, and that could not ſo eaſily ſwallow downe thoſe vanities and courſes which others doe not ſo much as ſcruple at; to her dying day ſhee did abhorre Popiſh and Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious vanities, and was much grieved that any ſhould take upon them to
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:28236:63"/> practiſe or maintaine any thing that was contrary to Gods Word, and juſtly ſcandalous unto Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</p>
            <p>Secondly, God had given<note place="margin">2. Loving<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to the godly.</note> her to become very loving hearted unto the godly; if ſhe ſaw in any but <hi>aliquid Chriſti</hi> (that is, ſomething of Chriſt) with holy <hi>Bucer,</hi> ſhee dearely loved them; the graces of God beſtowed on them drew her affections to them; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king her greatly to delight in their company and confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence; ſhee often would ſay to mee, where is the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure that ſinfull ſocieties can yeeld unto a Chriſtian? I am ſure I can finde no delight in being amongſt them; O it is the godly and ſuch as truly feare God that are my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:28236:63"/> and that ſhall be truly welcome unto my houſe, there are many Chriſtians this day alive that can teſtifie her reall love unto them a good patterne for us all to follow, wee ſhould make them the men of our company and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light here, that are our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions in grace, and ſhall be our company in Heaven.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, ſhee was large<note place="margin">3 Deſires and cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings after good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> hearted in her deſires after goodneſſe, and good things: a little heart ſhee had, but low, which made her very greedy after, and deſirous of grate ſuch a holy covetouſneſſe; and unſatiable thirſt was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted within her, that ſhee could never give her ſelfe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction in any preſent mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of grace, or actuall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of duties, but was
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:28236:64"/> carried with a vehement de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of bettering or mending her ſelfe in both; out of that deſire which ſhe had to profit and benefit her owne foule, and to augment and enlarge her ſelfe in graces and duties,<note place="margin">Hierony<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>i Epiſtolae ad Paulam, Marcellam &amp; alia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> (with thoſe religious Romane Ladies of whom S. <hi>Ierome</hi> ſpeakes,) ſhee would be full of holy enquiries, ſolid que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, and apt caſes of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; God gave unto her that excellent gift of improo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Chriſtian acquaintance and Chriſtian ſociety, for hardly could any good Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, or able Chriſtian come to viſit her in her health or ſickneſſe, but ſhee would be preſſing and putting of them on to ſome ſoule-profiting diſcourſe, by which ſhe might both doe her ſelfe and others
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:28236:64"/> good; oh it is a bleſſed thing for Chriſtians to bee acting <hi>Maries</hi> part, and I could hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily wiſh that in this ſhe might be followed in this City and other parts, for I finde this to be a common fault, that God puts into our hands ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny opportunities of doing our ſelves good by the company of Miniſters and Chriſtians, and wee have no hearts to improove them; wee thinke that when wee have feaſted them, and for a time courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly entertained them, wee have done enough; Oh how often hath mine eares heard her wiſhing, that ſhe had more power to beleeve, and ſpirit to pray and to obey; This Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of ours, made it her dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly worke to be treaſuring up a ſtocke of grace for another
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:28236:65"/> world, and the neerer ſhe was to glory, the more thirſtie was ſhe after grace. Surely where thoſe longings and thirſtings after ſoule enlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in graces and duties are wanting, there may bee a ſtrong ſuppoſition, that ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall life is alſo wanting. For herein doe artificiall bodies differ from naturall bodies, that the one are capeable of extenſion, the other are not.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, She was fearing<note place="margin">4. Fearfull of her owne ſtanding and ſtate.</note> hearted in reſpect of her ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall and eternall condition: ſhe did much trouble her ſelfe about that one thing neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, namely the ſetling of the happineſſe of her ſoule both here and hereafter; ſhee had an heart making Heaven to be Heaven, and it was a great buſineſſe with her, how ſhee
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:28236:65"/> might bee ſure to have Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven when ſhe left the world; ſhe was not in the number of thoſe, who onely then thinke of going to Heaven, when they ſee themſelves ready to drop into Hell; Neither was Heaven unto her an empty Notion, or going to Heaven an ordinary matter; but a thing of the higheſt concerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; ſhe knew that ſhe had a ſoule, and what it was to have a ſoule miſtaken, or miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carry in ſo great a matter as ſalvation; yea ſo ſerious was this Chriſtian Siſter of ours in this maine buſineſſe, that ſhee would often ſuſpect her owne care, and queſtion her owne evidences for Heaven, being ever and anon jealous leaſt that ſhee ſhould faile of Heaven at the laſt; This was
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:28236:66"/> admirable and imitable in her, that ſhee would be put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting her ſelfe to the triall, that ſo ſhee might ſee and finde her ſelfe to be Heaven proofe, and judgement proofe; and when upon long reaſoning and due triall, ſhee could not put of from her ſelfe the evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences of a gracious conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; out of a holy feare, ſhee brake out into theſe words; Sir, are you not miſtaken in your trialls? or in my ſelfe? I pray you to deale plainely and faithfully with my ſoule, doe not make me to beleeve that I am better then I am, or that my eſtate is ſafer then it is, remember that you are Gods Miniſter, and you muſt give an account to God if that you doe not diſcharge your duty, in diſcovering to me the truth
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:28236:66"/> of things: Let me know the worſt of mine eſtate, for I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire not, neither did I ſend for you to be ſlattered and ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed by you; O think of this all you that tie up the liberty and authority of Gods Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters when they come to vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit you, who cannot endure the ſetling of your ſpirituall eſtates by the ſearching of your ſoules.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, She was bold hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,<note place="margin">5. Zealous in ſpirit.</note> the fire of holy zeale was kindled within her ſpirit, and ſhee was ſo farre from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſhamed of God and his cauſe, that as occaſion was offered, and as it became her in her place, ſhee would ſpeake for God, and plead for the power and purity of His bleſſed worſhip and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice: yea ſhee kept that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:28236:67"/> to her ſelfe (which many looſe) namely, ſo to enjoy her beſt friends, that with all ſhe would wiſely diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like and Chriſtianly reproove what ſhee ſaw or heard to be amiſſe in them, which made ſuch as well knew her, the more truely to honour and love her.</p>
            <p>Sixtly, She was Heavenly<note place="margin">6. Heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dednes.</note> hearted; and dead to the world whilſt ſhee lived in the world; ſhee ſo minded her countrey in Heaven, that ſhe could willingly part with all the creatures for Heaven, nay ſhe had ſo ordered her affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and affaires, that ſhee had little elſe to doe but to die when ſhee was to die; well knowing that an heart ſet into the creatures, is loath to make an exchange of earth
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:28236:67"/> for Heaven, it was neither Husband, nor Children, nor Mother, nor Brothers or Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, nor Friends that could ſtand in her way, to make her loath or unwilling to die; they were all lookt upon with a dead eye long before ſhee died; it is a glorious conqueſt to get victory over the world and the creatures before a man dies.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, Shee was pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique<note place="margin">7. Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likenes of ſpirit.</note> hearted: having her ſpirit ſet upon the times, both in the ſins and ſorrowes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, being ſo ſenſible of both, that ſhe could bewaile both; and would be often in ſtirring up others to pray for <hi>Sions</hi> peace and glory. Oh how did ſhee rejoyce when ſhe ſaw any hopes of good towards the Church of God revived;
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:28236:68"/> and ſhee would be much caſt downe under the feares of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall calamities, fearing that her ſinnes were the procurers of the ſame.</p>
            <p>Eightly, She was bearing<note place="margin">8. Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</note> hearted: God put her pietie to proofe, laying his hand heavily upon her in much weakeneſſe, which kept her long under the Phiſitians hands, yet under all gods dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings ſhe was a patterne of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, quietly reſigning her ſelfe ſo to the good will and wiſedome of God, that ſhee did not checke or diſlike God in the courſe of his provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, but did acquit the Lord as righteous and juſt in his way, and did let him alone in his workes, being troubled at the riſing of impatiency within her; deſiring chieflly
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:28236:68"/> that God would be pleaſed to make her able to beare his hand, and to give her a ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied uſe of his hand, which ſhe knew would be for good unto her.</p>
            <p>Ninethly, Shee was ſtout<note place="margin">9. Stout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> hearted, which appeared in this, that ſhe did not feare the king of feare, death it ſelfe: I know that ſhee was very ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that the time of her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture was at hand, for ſhee apprehended more in her ſelfe, then the many skillfull Phyſitions could in her body, ſhe would tell mee that they were all miſtaken in her di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe, for ſhe ſhould not eſcape this ſickneſſe which was now upon her; and though ſhe did thinke much, and talke often of it, yet it was not death it ſelfe that could daunt or
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:28236:69"/> dampe her ſpirits; ſhe did no feare to die, having the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of this, that it was only death which could bring her unto her deſired home.</p>
            <p>Tenthly and laſtly, Shee<note place="margin">10. Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in death.</note> was confident hearted; her experience of <hi>God,</hi> and faith in <hi>God</hi> had raiſed up her ſoule to ſuch a truſt, in <hi>Gods</hi> mercy, that finding death approa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, ſhee left of diſputings with Satan, and fixing her eyes with much ſtedfaſtneſſe on Heaven, about the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Sabboth (which was the day of her delight whilſt ſhe lived, and I make no doubt a token unto her of an eternall reſt in Heaven) ſhe concluded her life with this ſaying, <hi>Death, Death, O Lord in thee is my truſt,</hi> which wordes of hers gave
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:28236:69"/> occaſion to her loving Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, to give unto mee that Text of Scripture to preach on at her funerall.</p>
            <p>And now leaving her<note place="margin">Applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Auditory.</note> whoſe ſoule is made perfect in Heaven, and free from all ſinne and ſorrow; give me your patience from the whole Narration, to leſſon you in theſe things, that ſo you may<note place="margin">4. Duties.</note> depart hence with profit.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, ſee the joyntnes of women with men, in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſalvation of Chriſtians, God hath given unto them ſoules as well as men, and he is pleaſed to make them as emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent in graces and gracious practiſes as he doth men, and therefore their ſex ſhould not be deſpiſed, nor their holy courſes ſcorned whilſt they doe but endeavour to ſave
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:28236:70"/> their poore ſoules.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly know, That the more gracious men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men are in their lives, the more comfortable ſhall they be in their deathes, and the more honourable after their deathes; ſuch ſeeke for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and credit in a wrong way, that doe not ſeeke it in a gracious way.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, Learne that wee muſt improove all the holy examples of Gods Saints, by following their courſes and<note place="margin">Exempla maxime movent. Cic de Orat lib. 3.</note> actions: the Heathen man telles us, that good examples are of great force: and ſure I am, that among Chriſtians this is a truth, that good ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples are of ſpeciall uſe and profit, and ſuch as we muſt be accountable for to God, as well as for precepts; we
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:28236:70"/> cannot doe greater honour to our religious Anceſtors decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, then to endeavour to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble them in goodneſſe and godlineſſe: Oh that you would all reſolve to go home being ſuch as ſhee was, and doing that which ſhee did of whom we have ſpoken.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Laſtly, Draw your owne deaths out of this occaſion; let it put you into dying thoughts, remember that you muſt all follow her that is gone before you, and how ſoone you know not, and that every ſtep of your life degrees you into the Chamber of death, you being here ſayling down times ſtreame into that gulph of death which enters you into Heavens or hels eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity: My beloved upon this ſhort and ſhortning time of
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:28236:71"/> yours which is uncertaine and irrevocable depends eternity; and if ever you will be wiſe for your ſoules, bee wiſe in this, to make your life the only providing time for Heavens eternity. And ſo much for the Text and the occaſion. <g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>Imprimatur</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>THO: WYKES.</signed>
               <date>Iuly 30. 1640.</date>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:28236:71"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
